I’d like to dedicate this one to all the women in South Africa --
أود أن أهدي هذه لجميع النساء في جنوب أفريقيا.
those women who refused to dwindle in the midst of apartheid.
هؤلاء النساء اللاتي رفضنّ التضاؤل في خضم الفصل العنصري.
And, of course, I’m dedicating it also to my grandmother,
وبالطبع، أهديه أيضاً إلى جدتي،
whom I think really played quite a lot of important roles,
والتي أعتقد أنها لعبت دوراً هاماً كبيراً،
especially for me when I was an activist, and being harassed by the police.
وخاصة بالنسبة لي عندما كنت ناشطا، وكنت أتعرض لمضايقات من قبل الشرطة.
You will recall that in 1976, June 16, the students of South Africa boycotted
تذكرون أنه في عام 1976، 16 يونيو، طلاب من جنوب أفريقيا قاطعوا
the language of Afrikaans as the medium of the oppressor,
اللغة الأفريقية بإعتبارها وسيلة من الظالم،
as they were sort of like really told
وكما تعلمون، وكانوا كأنهم قيل لهم بالفعل
that they must do everything in Afrikaans --
أن عليهم أن يمارسوا كل أمورهم باللغة الأفريقية --
biology, mathematics -- and what about our languages?
علم الأحياء، الرياضيات -- وماذا عن لغاتنا؟
And the students wanted to speak to the government,
والطلاب يريدون التحدث إلى الحكومة،
and police answered with bullets.
والشرطة تجيبهم بالرصاص.
So every year, June 16, we will commemorate
وهكذا كل عام، 16 يونيو، سيكون أحياء الذكرى
all those comrades or students who died.
كل أولئك الرفاق والطلاب الذين ماتوا.
And I was very young then. I think I was 11 years,
وكنت صغيراً جداً وقتها، أعتقد أنني كنت في الحادية عشرة من عمري،
and I started asking questions,
وبدأت أسأل أسئلة،
and that’s when my political education started.
وذلك عندما تعليمي السياسي، تعلمون، قد بدأ.
And I joined, later on, the youth organization
وأنضممت، بعد ذلك، لمنظمة الشباب
under the African National Congress.
عبر المجلس العالمي الأفريقي.
So as part of organizing this and whatever,
لذلك كجزء من المنظمة أو أي كان،
this commemoration, the police will round us up
في هذه الذكرى، الشرطة ستتجول حولنا
as they call us leaders.
كما تعلمون، إنهم يسموننا، القادة.
And I used to run away from home,
وكنت قد هربت من المنزل،
when I know that maybe the police might be coming
عندما علمت أن الشرطة رُبما تأتي
around the ninth or 10th of June or so.
في التاسع أو العاشر من شهر يونيو أو هكذا
And my grandmother one time said,
وجدتي، تعلمون، قالت ذات مرة،
"No, look, you’re not going to run away.
"لا مجال، لن تهرب.
This is your place, you stay here."
هذا مكانك، إبقى هنا."
And indeed, the police came -- because they’ll just arrest us
وبالفعل، حضرت الشرطة -- ﻷنهم فقط سيعتقلوننا
and put us in jail and release us whenever they feel like, after the 20th or so.
ويضعونا في السجن ويطلقوا صراحنا عندما يرغبوا بذلك، بعد 20 من يونيو أو هكذا.
So it was on the 10th of June, and they came, and they surrounded the house,
إذاً كان يوم 10 يونيو، عندما أتوا، وأحاطوا بالمنزل،
and my grandmother switched off all the lights in the house,
وقامت جدتي بإطفاء كل الأنوار في المنزل،
and opened the kitchen door.
وفتحت باب المطبخ.
And she said to them, "Vusi's here, and you're not going to take him tonight.
وقالت لهم، فيوزي هُنا، وأنتم لن تأخذوه الليلة.
I'm tired of you having to come here, harassing us,
انا تعبت من مجيئكم هنا، والتحرش بنا،
while your children are sleeping peacefully in your homes.
بينما ينام الأولاد بسلام في المنازل.
He is here, and you're not going to take him.
إنه هُنا، وأنتم لن تأخذوه.
I've got a bowl full of boiling water -- the first one who comes in here, gets it."
لدي طاسة مليئة بالماء الساخنة -- الذي سيدخل اولاً، يحصل عليها."
And they left.
و غادروا.
(Applause) (Music)
(تصفيق)
♫ Thula Mama, Thula Mama, Thula Mama, Thula Mama. ♫
♫ ثولا ماما، ثولا ماما، ثولا ماما، ثولا ماما. ♫
♫ Through the mist of the tears in your eyes on my childhood memory, ♫
♫ خلال الضباب الذى تصنعه دموع عينيك في ذاكرة طفولتي، ♫
♫ I know the truth in your smile, ♫
♫ أعرف الحقيقة في بسمتك، ♫
♫ piercing through the gloom of my ignorance. ♫
♫ تخترق كآبة جهلي. ♫
♫ Oh, there is a mama lying down sleeping ♫
♫ أوه، هنالك ماما تستلقي نائمة ♫
♫ you're very ill and your heart crying. ♫
♫ ترقدين مريضة جداً وقلبك يبكي. ♫
♫ Wondering, wondering, wondering, wondering where is this world coming to. ♫
♫ أتساءل، أتساءل، أتساءل، أتساءل لأين سيصير هذا العالم ♫
♫ Is it right the children have to fend for themselves? No, no, no, no, no. no. ♫
♫ هل صحيح أن الأطفال سيضطرون للدفاع عن أنفسهم؟ لا، لا، لا، لا، لا ♫
♫ Is it right heaping trouble on an old lady's head? ♫
♫ هل يصح أن نشغل بال إمراة عجوز بالهموم؟ ♫
♫ So unlucky faceless people. ♫
♫ أناس بلا وجوه خائبى الأمل. ♫
♫ Thula Mama Mama, Thula Mama. Thula Mama Mama. ♫
♫ ثولا ماما ماما، ثولا ماما، ثولا ماما ماما. ♫
♫ Thula Mama, Thula Mama, Thula Mama Mama, Thula Mama ♫
♫ ثولا ماما، ثولا ماما، ثولا ماما ماما، ثولا ماما♫
♫ Tomorrow it’s going to be better. ♫
♫ غداً سيكون أفضل.♫
♫ Tomorrow it's going to be better to climb, Mama. ♫
♫ غداً سيكون أفضل للصعود، ماما. ♫
♫ Thula Mama, Thula Mama. ♫
♫ ثولا ماما، ثولا ماما. ♫
♫ Am I to break into the song like the blues man or troubadour. ♫
♫ أنا أقتحم أغنية مثل رجل البلوز أو الشاعر المتجول. ♫
♫ And then from long distance in no blues club am I to sing, ♫
♫ ولا يلوح فى الأفق نادى للبلوز أغنى فيه، ♫
♫ baby, baby, baby, baby, baby, baby, baby, baby, baby, baby, baby, baby. ♫
♫ طفل، طفل، طفل، طفل، طفل، طفل، طفل، طفل، طفل، طفل، طفل، طفل. ♫
♫ Should I now stop singing of love, ♫
♫ هل يجب علي التوقف عن الغناء للحب، ♫
♫ now that my memory’s surrounded by blood? ♫
♫ بسبب الدماء التى تحيط بذاكرتى الان؟ ♫
♫ Sister, why oh why do we at times mistake a pimple for a cancer? ♫
♫ أختى، لماذا أه لماذا في أوقات نخطئ التمييز بين الدمل والورم السرطانى؟♫
♫ So who are they who says, no more love poems now? ♫
♫ إذا من الذى يقولون ، لا لمزيد من أشعار الحب الآن؟ ♫
♫ I want to sing a song of love ♫
♫ أريد أن أغني أغنية للحب ♫
♫ for that woman who jumped the fences pregnant ♫
♫ لتلك المرأة التي إجتازت السياج حاملة فى أحشائها جنين ♫
♫ and still gave birth to a healthy child. ♫
♫ وما زالت قادرة أن تلد طفلا سليما. ♫
♫ Softly I walk into the sun rays of the smile ♫
♫ بلطف مشيت في أشعة شمس الإبتسامة ♫
♫ that will ignite my love song, my song of life, ♫
♫ ما الذي سيشعل أغنية حُبي، أغنية حياتي، ♫
♫ my song of love, my song of life, my song of love, ♫
♫ أغنيتى للحب، أغنيتى للحياة، أغنيتى للحُب، ♫
♫ my song of life, my song of love, my song of life. ♫
♫ أغنيتى للحياة، أغنيتى للحُب، أغنيتى للحياة. ♫
♫ Ooh, I’ve not tried to run away from song, ♫
♫ أووه، لم أجرب أن أهرب من أغنية، ♫
♫ I hear a persistent voice, more powerful than the enemy bombs. ♫
♫ أسمع صوتا مصرا، أقوى كثيراً من قنابل الأعداء. ♫
♫ The song that washed our lives and the rains of our blood. ♫
♫ الأغنية التي غسلت حياتنا و دمائنا التى إنهمرت أمطارا. ♫
♫ My song of love and my song of life, my song of love, ♫
♫ أغنيتى للحُب وأغنيتى للحياة، أغنيتى للحُب، ♫
♫ my song of life, my song of love, ♫
♫ أغنيتى للحياة، أغنيتى للحُب، ♫
♫ my song of life, my song of love -- I want everybody to sing with me -- ♫
♫ أغنيتى للحياة، أغنيتى للحُب -- أريد كل شخص أن يغني معي -- ♫
♫ my song of life, my song of love, my song of life -- everybody sing with me -- ♫
♫ أغنيتى للحياة، أغنيتى للحُب، أغنيتى للحياة، -- جميعكم غنوا معي -- ♫
♫ my song of life, my song of love -- I can’t hear you -- ♫
♫ أغنيتى للحياة، أغنيتى للحُب -- لا أستطيع سماعكم -- ♫
♫ my song of love, my song of life -- you can do better -- ♫
♫ أغنيتى للحياة، أغنيتى للحُب -- يمكنكم فعل الأفضل -- ♫
♫ my song of life, my song of love -- keep singing, keep singing -- ♫
♫ أغنيتى للحياة، أغنيتى للحُب -- واصلوا الغناء، واصلوا الغناء -- ♫
♫ my song of love, my song of life, yes, my song of love -- ♫
♫ أغنيتى للحياة، أغنيتى للحُب، نعم، أغنية حُبي -- ♫
♫ you can do better than that -- ♫
♫ يمكنكم فعل أفضل من ذلك ♫
♫ my song of life, yes, my song of love, my song of life, my song of love -- ♫
♫ أغنيتى للحياة، أغنيتى للحُب، أغنية حياتي، أغنية حبي -- ♫
♫ keep singing, keep singing, keep singing -- my song of love. ♫
♫ واصلوا الغناء، واصلوا الغناء -- أغنية حبي. ♫
♫ Oh yeah. My song of -- a love song, my song of life. Sing. A love song, my song of life. Sing. ♫
♫ أوه نعم. أغنية -- أغنية حُب، أغنيتى للحياة. غنوا. أغنية للحُب، أغنيتى للحياة. غنوا. ♫
♫ Love song, my song of life. Sing. Love song, my song of life. Sing. ♫
♫ أغنية للحُب، أغنيتى للحياة. غنوا.. أغنية للحُب،أغنيتى للحياة. ♫
♫ Love song, my song of life. Sing. Love song, my song of life. ♫
♫ أغنية للحُب،أغنيتى للحياة، غنوا، أغنية للحُب، أغنيتى للحياة. ♫
♫ Love song, my song of life. ♫
♫ أغنية للحُب، أغنيتى للحياة. ♫
(Applause)
(تصفيق)